Subtitler filter for VirtualDub
Demonstration script
Avery Lee <phaeron@virtualdub.org>
Introduction
This script will demonstrate some of the simpler features of the subtitler. You will want to refer to the readme.txt file for a more complete reference.
Dialogue lines
Scripts are based on dialogue lines. Each dialogue line has a start time, an end time, and text to display in between.
0:00
[02:00-05:00] Hello.
[06:00-09:00] Oh, hi.
0:01
0:02
Hello.
[02:00-05:00] Hello.
0:03
0:04
0:05
[02:00-05:00] Hello.
0:06
Oh, hi.
[06:00-09:00] Oh, hi.
0:07
0:08
0:09
[06:00-09:00] Oh, hi.
0:10
Alignment
Dialogue lines may be placed in any of three horizontal placements and any of three vertical placements.
Bottom
left
center
Bottom
right
Top
left
center
Top
right
Middle
left
right
Text styles
Text may be varied in font, size, color, and style.
You can have your text in red, green, and blue; Courier; 16 point or 32 point; bold, italic, or even bold italic.
Wrapping styles
Three wrapping modes are supported: manual only, automatic wrapping, and smart wrapping. Smart wrapping is automatic wrapping, but with the lines broken as evenly as possible.
This line uses manual wrapping and won't
be wrapped except where explicitly broken.
This line uses automatic wrapping and is broken automatically.
This line uses smart wrapping and is broken with even lines. It's good for centered text.
Collisions
If two dialogue items attempt to display at the same time and place, the second one is pushed clear of the first. However, text stays in place after it is resolved, even if the collider disappears.
Man, I gotta get out of here!
Which way should I go? I'm not going back to school....
Ranma, you're in the way! Move!
Why would I move for an uncute tomboy like you?
Ranma no baka!!!
*wham*
Shadows and borders
You can vary the depth of the translucent shadow as well as the thickness and color of the border.
Border=0, shadow=0
Border=2, shadow=2 (red)
Border=2, shadow=6 (green)
Border=4, shadow=4 (blue)
Karaoke
Letting people sing to music is dangerous. But if they're going to do it anyway, they might as well have some help. Both snap and smooth styles are supported.
one two three-and four
DBCS (double-byte character set) support
If you have the appropriate language support installed, you can display far-east text in your subtitles. (By the way, I don't really know Japanese, so I'm kind of winged it above with the JWPce dictionary.)
[Keitarou]だ。。。大丈夫？
[Naru]何よ！
Motion effects
You can scroll text in like a banner, or up the screen.
Text is fun.  We like scrolling text.
You can scroll lots of text up this way. Personally, I find it a little annoying to have a lot of text coming up very slowly on screen, but it's a useful technique to have for credits and other long lists in tabular form.
Conclusion
That concludes the demo. I hope you've enjoyed the brief glimpse I've given you here, and encourage you to read the readme.txt file for more information on the effects you've seen here. Also, if you're bored, try loading this script into Kotus' Sub Station Alpha V4 program. Not all effects will render correctly, but most of the file will. Have fun, and keep on subtitling!
--Avery Lee <phaeron@virtualdub.org>
Author of VirtualDub and the 'subtitler' filter